A Guide to the Records of the First Virginia Chapter of the Association of Fundraising Professionals 1981-1997
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
A Guide to the Records of the First Virginia Chapter of the Association of Fundraising Professionals
Roanoke Public Libraries
2011.12.26
5 record storage boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
First Virginia Chapter, Association of Fundraising Professionals
Historical Information
In January of 2001 the National Society of Fundraising Executives (NSFRE) changed its name to Association of Fundraising Professionals (AFP). The Society had begun when the National Society of Fundraisers (NSFR) was chartered by the state of New York in June 1960. The first local chapter of NSFR was founded in New York City in July 1964 and had formerly been known as the Association of Fund Raising Directors (AFRD). In May 1965 the second chapter of NSFR was formed when the Fund Raisers Association of the National Capital, located in Washington, D.C., also joined NSFR. By the end of the 1970s there were 23 chapters, including one in Canada. In 1977 NSFR moved its national offices from New York to Washington, D.C. and changed its name to the National Society of Fundraising Executives (NSFRE). The First Virginia Chapter of NSFRE began formally meeting in October 1981. The name of the chapter was selected because it was the first chapter in the state of Virginia. Though the official charter date of the First Virginia Chapter of NSFRE was March 1982, preliminary meetings between founding members Clai Wilcox and Jesse Kent go back to early 1981. The first chapter newsletter was published in October 1981 and reported on the election of the first president of the chapter, Claiborne (Clai) Wilcox, Jr. In December 1981 the National Board of NSFRE approved the charter of the First Virginia Chapter of NSFRE, which became the 38th chapter of NSFRE. From the beginning, a primary purpose of the new chapter was to provide educational opportunities for members and the fund raising community. So the chapter began a successful series of institutes on fund raising, which became a national model for fund raising education. Certification became an important issue for the chapter, and many members sought and achieved certification. Chapter meetings were held on the second Tuesday of the month and the chapter’s newsletter was named The Second Tuesday in July 1982. The second (1983) president of the chapter, Jesse (Jess) E. Kent, collected and retained a large portion of the records contained in this collection. His records are by far the most numerous of the chapter presidents and extend far beyond his years in office, into the tenures of other presidents.
Scope and Content
The collection of First Virginia Chapter, Association of Fundraising Professionals Records 1981-1997 is contained in 5 record storage boxes, a total of 6.25 linear feet, and is located in the Virginia Room of the Roanoke Public Libraries in Roanoke, Virginia. All materials are foldered in acid free, labeled folders. The collection contains correspondence, financial records, membership lists, meeting agendas and minutes, newsletters, statements of goals and objectives, by-laws and other official records. There are many documents, programs, brochures and various records relating to institutes, conferences, workshops, and other educationally related professional activities sponsored by the chapter and other professional organizations for fund raisers, including the National Society of Fundraising Executives (NFSRE). Also included are detailed lists of presenters and attendees at institutes, workshops and various events sponsored by the chapter. Newspaper clippings related to chapter members and activities are interfiled with related materials. Some audio cassette tapes and VHS video tapes of educational programs are included among the other materials. The oldest dated run of materials in the collection coincides with the tenure of the first president of the chapter, Clai Wilcox, at the time of the founding of the chapter in 1981. The latest materials in the collection are from the tenure of chapter president Harold Uhl in 1997. The original order of the materials was retained in processing and there are several roughly chronological sequences in the collection, which mostly follow the tenures of the chapter presidents. However the order of materials is not strictly chronological and some presidential papers are not chronologically arranged. But to preserve the original order of the materials, the various series are arranged by presidential tenures as they appeared in the unprocessed AFP Collection. And the bulk of many of the materials come from the files of Jesse Kent, the second president of the chapter, who held the office in 1983, and who carefully collected and retained a large portion of the records contained in this collection throughout his association with the chapter. His records are by far the most numerous of the chapter presidents and extend far beyond his years in office into the tenures of other presidents. Some of the chapter presidents retained fewer records and so the documentation of their time in office is not as complete as others. The presidents of the First Virginia Chapter, Association of Fundraising Professionals, from the founding of the chapter through 1997, were: Clai Wilcox (1981-1982), Jesse Kent (1983), Jerry Ocorr (1984), Everett Werness (1985), J. Andreé Brooks (1986), David Prestipino (1987), Jennie Sue Murdock (1988), Donna Massey (1989), Bob Kulinski (1990), Jared (Jerry) Close (1991), Bill Bowen (1992), Linda Dodge (1993), Nancy Prillaman (1994), Gail Gregory (1995), Katherin Anderson (1996), and Harold Uhl (1997). Series are arranged under their names, but not strictly chronologically.
Arrangement
The documents are generally arranged chronologically by the President of the Chapter, though in some cases they are also arranged topically. The original order of the documents was maintained.
Contents List
- Records by President, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Claire Wilcox: Correspondence, financial records, meetings, clippings 1981-1982 (Folder 1)
  - Claire Wilcox: Newsletters, workshops-lists of attendees and presenters 1981-1982 (Folder 2)
  - Claire Wilcox: Charter members, by-laws, evaluations 1981-1982 (Folder 3)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Survey Course, 2 cassettes 1983 (Folder 4)
  - Jesse Kent: Newsletters 1983 (Folder 5)
  - Jesse Kent: Reports, minutes, correspondence 1983 (Folder 6-7)
  - Jesse Kent: Institute 1983 (Folder 8)
  - Jesse Kent: Boston conference 1983 (Folder 9)
  - Jesse Kent: Committees, by-laws 1983 (Folder 10)
  - Jesse Kent: Membership 1983 (Folder 11)
  - Jesse Kent: Seminars, news clippings 1983 (Folder 12)
  - Jerry Ocorr: Financial statements 1984 (Folder 13)
  - Jerry Ocorr: Institute, brochures, financial statements, list of participants 1984 (Folder 14)
  - Jerry Ocorr: Newsletters, brochures 1984 (Folder 15)
  - Jerry Ocorr: Membership lists 1984 (Folder 16)
  - Everett Werness: Harrison Heritage Center, news clippings, brochures, by-laws 1985 (Folder 17)
  - Jesse Kent: Brochures, newsletters 1985 (Folder 18)
  - Jesse Kent: Minutes 1985 (Folder 19-20)
  - Everett Werness: Certification, membership rosters, correspondence 1985 (Folder 21)
  - Everett Werness: Financial statements, agendas, newsletters, miscellaneous 1985 (Folder 22)
  - Everett Werness: Workbook 1985 (Folder 22-24)
  - Everett Werness: Financial statements, minutes 1985 (Folder 25)
  - David Prestipino: Minutes, financial statements, newsletters, miscellaneous 1987 (Folder 23)
- Records by President, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Jennie Sue Murdock: Minutes, newsletters, financial statements, miscellaneous 1988 (Folder 1)
  - Donna Massey: Newsletters, financial statements, miscellaneous 1989 (Folder 2)
  - Bob Kulinski: Minutes, newsletters, financial statements, miscellaneous 1990 (Folder 3)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Harrison Heritage and Cultural Center, Miscellaneous 1986 (Folder 4)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Philanthropy, National Philanthropy Day, newsletters, miscellaneous 1986 (Folder 5)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Special events seminars, Institute, financial statements, minutes, membership lists, miscellaneous 1986 (Folder 6)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Institute, miscellaneous 1986 (Folder 7)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Public relations, historian, photographs, negatives 1986 (Folder 8)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: NSFRE Institute 1986 (Folder 9)
  - Jesse Kent: Major Money video 1986 (Folder 10)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: Annual reports, newsletters 1986-1987 (Folder 11)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: NSFRE Board of Directors 1984-1986 (Folder 12)
  - J. Andreé Brooks: NSFRE Chapter Manual 1986 (Folder 13)
  - David Prestipino: By-laws, certification, agendas, minutes, Institute 1987 (Folder 14)
  - David Prestipino: Meetings, agendas, financial statements, miscellaneous 1987 (Folder 15)
  - Jennie Sue Murdock: Handbook, conference program 1988 (Folder 16)
  - Jennie Sue Murdock: Chapter manual, by-laws, minutes, financial statements, miscellaneous 1988 (Folder 17-18)
  - Jennie Sue Murdock: Library, minority outreach, miscellaneous 1988 (Folder 19)
  - Jennie Sue Murdock: The Idea Machine video 1988 (Folder 20)
  - Donna Massey: Miscellaneous, membership, meetings, financial statements, keychains, diskette of back issues of NSFRE newsletters, 1989 (Folder 21)
- Records by President, 1989-1994 (Box 3)
  - Donna Massey: Miscellaneous, meetings, programs, financial statements 1989 (Folder 1)
  - Donna Massey: Committees, Institute, library, philanthropy, newsletter, publicity 1989 (Folder 2)
  - Donna Massey: Committees, Institute, miscellaneous 1989 (Folder 3)
  - Bob Kulinski: Meetings, minutes, financial statements, newsletters, surveys 1990 (Folder 4)
  - Bob Kulinski: Meetings, minutes, financial statements, newsletters, surveys 1990 (Folder 5)
  - Jesse Kent: Miscellaneous, seminar, by-laws 1991 (Folder 6)
  - Jesse Kent: Miscellaneous, mission, certification 1990 (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, certification 1990 (Folder 8)
  - Jesse Kent: Statewide conferences on volunteerism, resumes, correspondence 1990 (Folder 9)
  - Jesse Kent: The Capital Campaign 1990, financial statements, correspondence, newsletters 1990 (Folder 10)
  - Jesse Kent: Special Event Fundraising 1990 (Folder 11)
  - Jared Close: Goals and objectives, minutes, meetings, investments, newsletters 1991 (Folder 12)
  - Jared Close: Financial statements, newsletters, conferences 1991 (Folder 13)
  - Bill Bowen: By-laws, list of files, nominations, conferences, miscellaneous 1992-1993 (Folder 14)
  - Bill Bowen: Conferences, newsletters, meetings, financial reports 1992-1993 (Folder 15)
  - Linda Dodge: Membership, conferences, financial reports, miscellaneous 1993-1994 (Folder 16)
  - Linda Dodge: Meetings, newsletters, financial reports, miscellaneous 1993-1994 (Folder 17)
  - Linda Dodge: By-laws, policies, miscellaneous 1993-1994 (Folder 18)
  - Nancy Prillaman: Annual report, goals, income tax form, financial reports, meetings, minutes, 1994-1995 (Folder 19)
  - Nancy Prillaman: Chapter service program, financial records, membership, meetings, correspondence, newsletters 1994-1995 (Folder 20)
  - Nancy Prillaman: Chapter service program, financial records, minutes, membership, correspondence, newsletters 1994-1995 (Folder 21)
- Records by President, 1995-1997 (Box 4)
  - Nancy Prillaman: Minutes, meetings, reports, financial reports, recognition luncheon, miscellaneous 1994-1995 (Folder 1)
  - Gail Gregory: Minutes, newsletter, financial statements, IRS form, miscellaneous 1995-1996 (Folder 2)
  - Gail Gregory: Minutes, newsletter, financial statements, policies, nominations, miscellaneous 1995-1996 (Folder 3)
  - Gail Gregory: Minutes, newsletter, 1995 National Philanthropy Day 1995-1996 (Folder 4)
  - Katherin Anderson: National Philanthropy Day 1995 (Folder 5)
  - Katherin Anderson: National Philanthropy Day 1996 (Folder 6)
  - Katherin Anderson: National Philanthropy Day Manual 1996 (Folder 7)
  - Harold Uhl: NSFRE Anniversary Celebration 1997 (Folder 8)
  - Harold Uhl: Newsletters, financial statements, goals, minutes, also includes information from Katherin Anderson 1997 (Folder 9)
  - Jesse Kent: Fundraising Conference 1992 (Folder 10)
  - Jesse Kent: Fundraising Conference 1992 (Folder 11)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Institute planning 1992 (Folder 12)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Institute planning 1993 (Folder 13)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Institute planning 1994 (Folder 14)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Institute planning 1995 (Folder 15)
  - Jessie Kent: NSFRE Institute and National Conference 1995 (Folder 16)
  - Jesse Kent: NSFRE Institute, news clippings 1995 (Folder 17)
  - Jesse Kent: Roanoke Museum of Fine Arts Study Report 1990 (Folder 18)
  - Jesse Kent: Roanoke Museum of Fine Arts miscellaneous documents 1990 (Folder 19)
  - Jesse Kent: Roanoke Museum of Fine Arts interview forms and miscellaneous documents 1990 (Folder 20)
  - Jesse Kent: Roanoke Museum of Fine Arts brochures and exhibition catalogs 1990 (Folder 21)
- Jesse Kent Records, 1982-1992 (Box 5)
  - Giles Memorial Hospital 1987 (Folder 1)
  - Objectives, meetings, glossary, membership, miscellaneous records 1990 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous collection of citations 1968 (Folder 3)
  - NSFRE Membership Directory 1985 (Folder 4)
  - Special events, miscellaneous correspondence unknown (Folder 5)
  - By-laws, special events unknown (Folder 6)
  - Membership list unknown (Folder 7)
  - NSFRE Correspondence, Fall membership drive 1986 (Folder 8)
  - Membership drives, by-laws 1984-1985 (Folder 9)
  - Satellite videoconference program guide for Major Money 1986 (Folder 10)
  - NSFRE correspondence, membership lists, miscellaneous 1982, 1986, 1990 (Folder 11)
  - NSFRE Institute 1989 (Folder 12)
  - NSFRE Institute brochures and guides 1989 (Folder 13)
  - NSFRE First Virginia Chapter conference on fund raising 1984 (Folder 14)
  - NSFRE correspondence, certification, brochures, newsletters, miscellaneous 1986-1990 (Folder 15)
  - NSFRE certification, newsletters, International Conference, miscellaneous 1990-1992 (Folder 16)
  - Charitable contributions undated (Folder 17)
  - Fundraising Seminar 1988 (Folder 18)
  - Certification, miscellaneous unknown (Folder 19)
  - NSFRE/PRSA Institute 1984 (Folder 20)
  - 4 audio cassette tapes, unlabelled undated (Folder 21)
  - NSFRE certification undated (Folder 22)
  - NSFRE certification 1984 (Folder 23)
  - NSFRE certification, membership roster undated (Folder 24)
  - NSFRE certification, glossary 1990 (Folder 25)
  - NSFRE seminars 1990, 1992 (Folder 26)